# ZHAI, Dongfang

Male The Education University of Hong Kong Phone: +86 186 1253 6186

Birth in Jun 1985 MA in Chinese Studies (Language Education) Gmail: <a href="mailto:bienfantaisie@gmail.com">bienfantaisie@gmail.com</a>
Married Grade: Distinction, Top 5% Portfolio: <a href="mailto:http://futurefriendly.cn/me">http://futurefriendly.cn/me</a>



- ZHAI is a UX designer who prefers social, content and education related products. He holds a master degree in the major of Chinese language & literature, as X-shaped, he has 10 years of experience on Web design and front-end development.
- Since 2011, ZHAI has paid his attention in Content Strategy area. The "Future Friendly Web Design thinking" which was established by Jeremy Keith and friends was selected by ZHAI as the core methodology, it means that "Content First", "Mobile First" and "Orbital Content" are the most important and significant rules in the design process.



# Experience

#### Jul 2015 - Dec 2016: Lead Interaction Designer; Hitch Group; DiDi CHUXING (Beijing)

- Interaction design for native APP and mobile web pages. Established Hitch's own design system (Guideline), built design tools<sup>2</sup>. ZHAI drew storyboards for operation pages and implemented the animation elements with CSS. for an instance, in 2015 mid-autumn operation activity, the 30-second duration animation page costs 6 man-days, thus we obtained 1.2 million PV data, 170 thousand sharing times on the WeChat platform.
- Organized tech exchange activities with different teams from different corporations. For example, The group of Tencent "YUTU" used to be invited to make a training on how to apply HTML5 page builder. "IMAYAN" QR Code design group used to be invited to share professional topics with our team. On the other hand, ZHAI hold the internal design—tech sharing events for 7 times, he had talked 2 topics below: "From Voice & Tone to Content Strategy", "The Overview of Web Design".

#### Apr 2015 - Jul 2015: Senior Interaction Designer; Institute of Data Science & Technologies; ALIBABA INC. (Beijing)

- Interaction design for the built-in search engine on Alibaba Cloud Operation platform (a.k.a. *YunOS*). To ensure the smooth experience on low RAM devices, we had promoted to reduce the memory usage by 10% on specified function.
- Collaborated with Taobao mobile design team, hold discussions on competitive products analysis and tech pre-research.

#### May 2011 - Apr 2015: UI Developer / Interaction Designer; Online Media Group; TENCENT (Beijing)

- ZHAI was a UI developer served *Tencent Weibo* and *Weishi* before May 2014. Then became an interaction designer served *Tencent Weibo*, *Weishi* and *Tencent News Client*.
- In Aug 2012, ZHAI was involved in the "Tencent Weibo Online Cheer Group" web project which was prepared for the London Olympics. As a UI developer, he successfully supported the product to receive more than 20 million CHEER action data and more than 2 million FOLLOW action data during the active period, exceeded sales expectation by 17 times. In Oct 2013, ZHAI had supported the responsive design for early Weishi's website and managed the components library in a real-time way. In Nov 2013, for the reason of function expanded, ZHAI had refactored the front-end code for removing the structure of the responsive design and relaunched the project within 24 hours. The size of assets reduced by 50%, thus saved 700,000 RMB of bandwidth cost per years since then. In addition, from Sep 2012 to May 2014, there were 25 times of

٠

www.futurefriendly.cn

www.futurefriendly.cn/ufoanimate/

- design sharing meeting were organized by ZHAI, 8 to 40 colleagues were involved each time, 57 topics were totally covered. In Aug 2013, ZHAI gave a lecture named "Responsive Web Design" with the support of Tencent design council.
- Completed the following internal courses: Project Management Foundation, Advanced Design Project Management, User
  Research Basics, Methodology of UX Design, Micro-Innovation, Website Front-end Structure Design, Website Performance
  Optimization, The Pyramid Principle, Time Management, Five Star Communications, How to Make Sharing More Effective,
  How to Be A Successful Mentor. Outstanding Staff Award 2012; Best Creative Award in Tencent Weibo Design Competition
  2013; Silver Award in TAL Education Innovation Competition 2013; Silver Award in Tencent Hackathon 2014.

Apr 2010 - May 2011: Web Front-end Engineer; Department of Web Products; RISING INT'L SOFTWARE CO., LTD. (Beijing)

• Front-end implementing on SNS project.

May 2008 - Apr 2010: Project Manager; Internet Dept.; VCHOICE ERA DESIGN CONSULTANT CO., LTD. (Beijing)

 Responsible for project management of an portal website, promotion and design works. This platform provided differentiated services for different roles in the exhibition industry, the profit model was mainly exhibition journal subscription. In addition, he used to serve the following customers as a graphic designer: DLSP2009, Chindex, Minmetals, Savinelli, etc.

Jul 2006 - Apr 2008: Certification Assistant; Certification Dept.; CHINA CERTIFICATION & INSP. GROUP (Zhengzhou)

Responsible for arranging the audit team for enterprises in Henan province. ISO9000 documents management.



# Other Projects Experience

- 2015: Interaction design for epubit.com, the online e-book store of Post & Telecom Press.
- 2014: Redesigned the int'l official website of Peking University<sup>2</sup>, including UI development work (HTML/CSS/Bootstrap).



# Education

#### 2017 - 2018: Master of Arts in Chinese Studies (Language Education); THE EDUCATION UNIVERSITY OF HONG KONG

- Supervisor Dr. CHAN, Chi Tak, GPA3.54, Distinction Award (top 5%), Dean's Honour List.
- Majoring linguistics courses included: Pragmatics, Different Community Words Between Cantonese and Putonghua, etc.
- In Sep 2018, one of ZHAI's research thesis focused on literature and culture studies was published at the 37<sup>th</sup> "Studies in Chinese Literature" seminar held by Liberal Arts College of National Taiwan University.

## 2009 - 2013: Bachelor of Arts in Chinese Language & Literature; BEIJING NORMAL UNIVERSITY



## **Publications**

- 2017: Translated: Aaron Gustafson's "Adaptive Web Design" (Post & Telecom Press, ISBN: 9787115448484).
- 2017: Translated: Stephen A. Thomas' "Data Visualization with JavaScript" (Post & Telecom Press, ISBN: 9787115444356).



# Skills

- Persona, Usability, Accessibility, Brainstorming, Copywriting, Storyboarding, Prototyping, Data Visualization, Progressive Enhancement, Responsive Web Design.
- Mind Map, Markdown, Sketch/Axure, Adobe Design Suite, SVG, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, Bootstrap, LESS, Gulp, Git/SVN, Fiddler/Charles, Weinre.

www.slideshare.net/bienfantaisie/webrebuild-as-design/

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>®</sup> newsen.pku.edu.cn

# 翟东方

出生: 1985.6生源: 河南郑州专业: 中文研究(语文教育)邮箱: <br/>bienfantaisie@gmail.com婚否: 已婚现居: 北京昌平成绩: Distinction, Top 5%网站: http://futurefriendly.cn/me



自述

• 中国语言文学专业。社交、内容、教育领域的互联网从业者,在行业内拥有广泛人脉。

对内容策略的关注和和研究始于 2011 年,以 Jeremy Keith 等人参与的"面向未来的友好设计"为方法论,即内容优先、移动优先、用户中心的三原则。



#### 工作经验

### 2015.7 - 2016.12: 交互设计负责人; 顺风车事业部; 北京嘀嘀无限科技发展有限公司

- Native APP 以及社交传播导向 H5 的交互设计。设计体系规范搭建,开发设计工具<sup>®</sup>。开创了以动画讲故事的 H5 形式,以 2015 中秋活动 30 秒动画 H5 为例,团队投入 6 人天,PV120 万,微信分享 17 万次。
- 组织外部资源交流,如腾讯 "*玉兔*" H5 制作平台培训、"*码眼无界"* 二维码设计方法分享。团队内部组织设计技术沟通交流会 7 期,主讲 《情感化内容策略》、《Web 设计基础》等主题。

#### 2015.4 - 2015.7: 高级交互设计师;数据科学与技术研究院;北京阿里巴巴云计算技术有限公司

- 负责阿里*云 OS* 内置搜索引擎的交互设计。为了确保内存较小设备上的动画体验流畅,推动开发团队将手机端*云 OS* 的内存占用减少 10%。
- 与手淘团队合作,组织竞品分析、技术预研和设计交流。

#### 2011.5 - 2015.4: UI 开发工程师/交互设计师; 网络媒体事业群; 腾讯科技(北京)有限公司

- 2011年5月起任UI开发工程师,服务*腾讯微博、微视*; 2014年5月起任交互设计师,服务*腾讯微博、新闻客户端、微视*。
- 2012 年 8 月,*伦敦奥运微博助威团*项目。作为 UI 开发支持活动总助威次数和广播数超 2000 万,直接收听量 200 万,超出销售预期 17 倍。2013 年 10 月,*微视* PC 端立项,提供响应式设计支持,维护设计组件库。2013 年 11 月,*微视*产品形态扩张,24小时内拆除响应式设计,缩小 50%文件体积并重新上线,节省 70 万元人民币/年带宽成本。此外,2012 年 9 月至 2014 年 5 月,组织部门内外分享会 25 期,涉及 57 个主题,每期 8—40 人出席。2013 年 8 月,主讲腾讯内部课程:《响应式设计》》。
- 完成以下腾讯内部课程的学习:《项目管理基础》、《设计项目管理进阶》、《用户研究基础》、《体验设计方法论》、《微创新解读》、《网站前端架构设计》、《网站性能优化》、《金字塔思维》、《时间管理》、《五星级沟通》、《如何令分享更有效》、《如何成为卓有成效的导师》。2012 年腾讯优秀员工。2013 年腾讯微博创新创业大赛最佳创意奖。2013 年首届好未来教育创新大赛银奖。2014年第二届腾讯创意马拉松银奖。

#### 2010.4 - 2011.5: Web 前端工程师; Web 产品部; 北京瑞星信息技术有限公司

• 负责 SNS 项目的前端开发。

#### 2008.5 - 2010.4: 项目经理; 网络部; 北京维创时代企业策划有限责任公司

• 2008 年 5 月,负责垂直门户网站的立项及项目管理,电话销售,展会宣传工作。该平台为展会主办方、承办方、服务商提供差异化服务。以会刊订阅为盈利模式。另曾以平面设计服务下列客户: DLSP2009、美中互利、中国五矿、中国网、Savinelli 等。

-

<sup>\*\*</sup> www.futurefriendly.cn

www.futurefriendly.cn/ufoanimate/

www.slideshare.net/bienfantaisie/webrebuild-as-design/

#### 2006.7 - 2008.4: 认证主办;认证部;中国检验认证集团

• 负责安排河南地区审核组,管理1万家企业ISO9000族审核材料。



# 其他项目

• 2015: 主持设计开发人民邮电出版社线上销售平台"异步社区"。

• 2014: 改版设计北京大学国际版官方网站<sup>2</sup>,含 UI 开发工作(HTML/CSS/Bootstrap)。



# 教育

# 2017 - 2018: 中文研究 (语文教育) 硕士; 香港教育大学

- 导师陈智德博士。毕业成绩优(GPA3.54, Distinction Award, top 5%),综合表现获院长荣誉状(Dean's Honour List)。
- 主修语言学课程包括语用学、广州话与普通话社区词比较研究等。
- 2018年9月,参加国立台湾大学文学院主办的第37届《中国文学研究》学术研讨会并发表论文。

#### 2009 - 2013: 汉语言文学学士; 北京师范大学



#### 出版物

- 2017: 翻译出版《渐进增强:跨平台用户体验设计》(ISBN: 9787115448484),五八赶集集团 CTO 邢宏宇推荐。
- 2017:翻译出版《UavaScript 数据可视化编程》(ISBN: 978711544435), 云峰金融集团 CEO 李婷推荐。

# 技能

- 用户绘像、可用性、可访问性、头脑风暴、文案、故事板、快速原型、数据可视化、渐进增强、响应式设计。
- 思维导图、Markdown、Sketch/Axure, Adobe Design Suite, SVG, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, Bootstrap, LESS, Gulp, Git/SVN, Fiddler/Charles, Weinre。

www.epubit.com.cn

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup> newsen.pku.edu.cn